# 大家好 好久都沒進過那竹鼠棚裡面去啦
Hi everyone! It has been a long time since my last time going into the bamboo rats shed.
# 帶大家進去看一下那裡沒有 沒竹鼠了哦
Let me take you there and have a look. There are no, no more bamboo rats now.
# 小狗 小羊
Doggy! Hey goat!
# 你看 全是亂糟糟的
Look! It’s a big piece of mess.
# 你看 這個池子還是很漂亮的哦 剛做沒多久的
Look! These cells are still very pretty, you know. They’re newly built.
# 放一個公仔圶這裡 看下怎麼樣
Let me put a stuffed toy here, and see how it looks.
# 像不像真的
Does it look like a real one?
# 這個可以放在這裡 誒 這裡要掃一下
I can put this one here. Eh? Here needs to be cleaned.
# 你看 以前每天都掃 現在 不用掃啦
Look! I used to clean them every day. But now, no need.
# 你看 習不習慣
Look! Do you like this place?
# 你看 這樣放下去很可愛哦
Look! It’s so cute inside the cell,
# 就是不會動的
except that it doesn’t move.
# 你看 摸起來很舒服吧 這個毛
Look! The fur feels really good, the fur.
# 看搞的跟真的一樣 有點硬邦邦的
It really looks like the real fur. It’s a bit stiff.
# 你看 它牙齒都白了 肯定上火了
Look! Its teeth are all white. It must have eaten too much junk food.
# 給它 給一些
Let me give it, give it some,
# 給一些那個下火的東西給它吃就好啦 (註︰已經不是真竹鼠，不太講究，容易明白就算了)
some it some more healthy food. It will soon be fine.
# 尾巴那麼短
Its tail is so short.
# 打架了
It must have had a fight.
# 這爪子 它的爪子
This claws, its claws,
# 好鋒利啊它的爪子 看上去就很鋒利
Its claws are really sharp. They look very sharp.
# 搞不痛的 絨毛做的
It doesn’t hurt. Cuz they’re made of flannel.
# 要是真的我就不敢給它這樣抓
If wouldn’t dare to let it scratch me if it’s real.
# 好像啊哦
It really looks like a real one.
# 捏兩下
Let me squeeze it.
# 這個不怕它咬啦這個
There’s no risk of being bitten, with this bamboo rat.
# 鬍子怎麼沒有啦 鬍子
Why aren’t there any whiskers? Where are the whisker?
# 鬍子容易抓了 容易抓 抓人的臉
The whisker may scratch, they always scratch, scratch our faces.
# 鬍子都被我拔掉啦
So I pulled out all whiskers.
# 你看公仔
Have a look at this toy.
# 放在這裡
I put it here,
# 放成一排
in a line.
# 站穩來哦 別掉不去了
Stand still. Don’t fall.
# 多可愛
So cute!
# 排隊
Line up!
# 一二三四五六七八九十
One two three four five six seven eight nine ten
# 這樣就漂亮啦這樣
Now it’s really pretty, pretty.
# 要竹鼠有那麼聽話就好了
Why aren’t the real bamboo rats as nice as they are?
# 你看 把它收回了
Look! I’m gonna get them back.
# 這個池子 明天就準備把它全部拆掉啦
These cells, I'll start pulling them down tomorrow.
# 不用啦 也用不上啦
I don’t need them anymore, not now, nor in the future.
# 來 裝到袋子這邊來
C’mon! Put them into the bag.
# 你看 這個池子很好拆的哦
Look! Pulling down the cells doesn’t take too much effort.
# 這個剛做沒兩年
They’re newly built, less than two years ago.
# 可能還可以有 其它的利用
Perhaps they can still be used, somewhere else.
# 或者把這個把它 看下有沒有需要的
I could perhaps take them, take it and see if anyone wants them.
# 需要的就買[SIC]給它算啦
I can sell them these boards.
# 這些瓷磚也是要錢來買的
Afterall, I did pay for these boards.
# 明天就把它全部拆掉
I’ll pull them all down tomorrow.
# 不要啦 把這裡清理一下
Let them go. Then I’ll clean this place,
# 養點其它東西
and keep some other livestock.
# 拆的時候很容易拆的哦 一拆就倒啦
Pulling down is easy. A single pull is everything needed.
# 做的時 做的話這裡最少要做兩個月
But building them, building them needs at least two months.
# 如果一個人的話可能要兩三個月才能做的完
It may take up to three months if they’re built alone.
# 要慢慢粘 要要黏 還要固定
You need to glue them, stick them, and place them well, step my step.
# 一個人拆太累了
Doing it alone is too exhausting.
# 叫兄弟 明天叫兄弟這來一起拆
I’ll ask my buddy, ask my buddy to come tomorrow and do it together with me.
# 看一下那個小豬 昨天都沒餵 今天
Let me have a look at the piggy. I didn’t feed it yesterday. So today,
# 它應該餓著了 去搞點那個玉米來給它吃
it must be staving now. I’m gonna get some corns for it.
# 先來餵一下它
Let me feed it first.
# 拿了玉米上來 這個小豬最喜歡吃的這個玉米
So I have the corns with me now. It's the piggy's most favourite food.
# 它一天就吃那麼一丟丟就夠啦 不要吃那麼多
Just a tiny little bit here is enough for a day. Don’t let it eat too much.
# 吃多了它容易胖
Eating too much may lead to obesity.
# 來 妹妹過來呀 餵小豬咯
C’mon! Come here my girl. We’re gonna feed the piggy.
# 你怕不怕
Are you scared?
# 你怕不怕小豬
Are you scared of piggy?
# 還有鴨鴨哦
There’s also ducky,
# 還有鵝鵝哦
and goose.
# 走邊上
Walk on the side.
# 拿給它們吃
Give it to them.
# 你看這小豬太壞啦 它趕那個鴨子
Look! This piggy is really mean. It’s chasing away the duck.
# 是不小豬佩琪這條
Is this one Peppa Pig?
# 是不是
Is it?
# 小豬佩琪是不是這一隻
Is Peppa Pig in front of us?
# 你敢不敢去騎豬豬 敢不敢
Do you dare to ride on the piggy? Do you?
# 敢不敢
Do you dare?
# 嘿嘿 丟掉啦
Hehe. It dropped.
# 快把它撿回來
Let me pick it up.
# 好像又胖了 大了好多 現在
It seems that it has put on weight again. It’s so much bigger now.
# 摸一下它 看它還有沒有反應
Let me touch it and see if what happens.
# 過來
Come here!
# 那麼兇幹嘛 這裡又沒人搶你的
How come are you so fierce? The corns are yours and only yours.
# 暈了
It’s falling down.
# 它要吃 如果沒東西吃的話它就躺下啦
It wants to eat. It may lie down if it’s not eating.
# 我怎麼一模它腳都站不穩了 呵呵呵
Why is my touch making it shaky? Ho ho ho!
# 嘿耶 不讓我碰
Heya! It refuses my touch.
# 你看 這個鴨子好肥啦 都下蛋啦
Look! This duck is very fat now. It lays eggs now.
# 鵝也是 下的蛋都被這條豬偷吃了
The goose too. But their eggs are all stolen by this pig.
# 你看 這些攀蒲 種的那麼茂盛 都是前面那條豬種的哦
Look! These pumpkins, they’re growing so well. These are all planted by the pigs that used to live here, you know.
# 有一句話怎麼說來的
How does the saying go?
# 前豬種 種瓜 後豬爽歪歪
Pumpkins, and, and veggies, pigs plant for their heirs.
# 很爽口的哦 這個攀蒲
The pumpkins, are really crunchy.
# 現在豬跟羊 跟鵝 跟鴨 都相處在一起了
The pig is now getting along with the goat, the goose and the duck.
# 而且很和諧的哦 不打架 不吵也不鬧
And they get along well, you know. No fights, no arguments, no quarrels.
# 誰干打架 誰敢吵 一鍋端了你
Anyone who dares to make a scene here, I’ll put you into the pot.
# 咩~
Meh~
# 肚子好大啦這隻羊
This goat now has a very big belly.
# 你看 它這個豬的豬身好長啊看著
Look! This pig, its body is really long. See?
# 原 原來是圓的 現在是加長啦
It used, used to be round. But now it’s much longer.
# 說明又胖了
That means it’s fatter.
# 又長大了一點
It has grown up a bit again.
# 到過年的時候這應長到一百多斤
It would be well over fifty kilograms by the Chinese New Year.
# 剛好 對半劈開
Cut it into half. Perfect!
# 我和攝影小 我和攝影小哥一人一半
I and Mr. Camer, I and Mr. Cameraman each takes half.
# 從中間一破
Split it into two parts from the middle.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 我要回家煮飯啦
I need to go home and cook for my dinner.